All right, good morning. I'm Dan Margulis filling in for Rabbi Linzer
while he is away. Today is March 25th, it is שושן פורים,
Shushan Purim, the 15th of אדר. Adar. It is שלושים יום קודם
החג. shloshim yom kodem hachag. We start שואלים ודורשים בהלכות הפסח. shoalim
vedorshim behilchot hapesach. I thought we were doing מסכת קידושין. Masechet Kiddushin.
That's what we're doing מסכת קידושין. Masechet Kiddushin. It's important to think
כל התורה כולה עניין אחד. kol hatorah kula inyan echad. We have
all sorts of things we can learn for פסח, Pesach, but also
the important point about הלכות פסח, Hilchot Pesach, שואלים ודורשים, shoalim vedorshim,
the first thing we ask is that we ask questions. So that's
the important point about פסח. Pesach. Okay, lots of questions. So we're
in the middle of the סוגיה sugya here on יג עמוד ב
yud gimmel amud bet talking about how do we know that if
the husband dies, that means that a woman could remarry? And this
is actually an important polemical point against certain religions who understand that
there are eternal marriages that last even after one of the two
spouses passes away, and so it's important to reject that notion.
Why, was that the religion at the time of the גמרא? Gemara?
I'm not sure if it was the religion at the time of
the גמרא. Gemara. There certainly are religions around today that believe in
such things. I think the Mormons believe in an eternal marriage even
after death.
No, no, it's very complicated. It's complicated.
Anyway, more than one wife after death.
Okay. So the גמרא Gemara has tried to determine a few different
דרשות drashot and we're towards the bottom where the גמרא Gemara says,
towards the middle-ish bottom, the גמרא Gemara says אלא מדאמר רחמנא אלמנה
לכהן גדול אסורה הא לכהן הדיוט שריא. ela mideamar rachmana almanah lekohen
gadol asura ha lekohen hedyot sharya.
So what about just learning from the fact that there was a
special prohibition for a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol to marry an אלמנה,
almanah, that means even a regular כהן kohen could marry an אלמנה
almanah and therefore an אלמנה almanah is allowed to remarry, even to
a כהן, kohen, and the only person who's not allowed to marry
an אלמנה almanah would be a כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. ודילמא לכהן
גדול בלאו לכולי עלמא בעשה? vedilma lekohen gadol belav lekulei alma beasei?
Maybe there's a negative mitzvah for a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol to
marry an אלמנה, almanah, but everyone else, that is ישראלים Yisraelim and
כהנים Kohanim and everyone else, would have an
איסור עשה, issur asei, because the רי Ri in תוספות Tosafot suggests
the possibility maybe from the פסוק pasuk ודבק באשתו, vedavak beishto,
the idea that there's a מצות עשה mitzvat asei to be joined
with your wife, and therefore even after death that might prohibit another
man to be...
Wait, you can't דרשן darshan an איסור דאורייתא issur deoraita from a
פסוק pasuk that's not even there on...
Well, you can דרשן darshan an איסור דאורייתא issur deoraita from whatever
פסוק pasuk you want. Oh, you're saying in the גמרא? Gemara? Well,
it's תוספות. Tosafot. The רי Ri can do whatever he wants.
No, but I'm saying this is the גמרא's Gemara הוה אמינא. hava
amina.
Right, the גמרא Gemara has a הוה אמינא. hava amina. All of
this שקלא וטריא shakla vetarya is going to be rejected. That is,
the whole notion here is just to push us on the notion
of something we would have thought was incredibly intuitive and obviously that
the גמרא Gemara had even told us סברא הוא, sevara hu, nonetheless,
we actually do have פסוקים psukim to derive it, and it's an
interesting question what הוה אמינא hava amina is motivating the thrust to
make sure we understand that a widow can remarry is a well-grounded
notion. But okay.
אלא לכהן גדול בלאו ולכולי עלמא בעשה. ela lekohen gadol belav ulekulei
alma beasei. האי עשה מאי עביד ליה אי דאהני מיתת הבעל תשתרי
לגמרי אי לא אהני מיתת הבעל תוקמה במילתא קמייתא.
hai asei mai avid lei ei
deahani mitat habaal tishari legamre ei lo ahani mitat habaal tukma bemilta
kamaisa. So maybe that the מצות עשה... mitzvat asei... So
in other words, like what does this מצות עשה mitzvat asei do
differently? Because either you're still back where you were, or it's not
any difference because מיתת הבעל, mitat habaal, how can you get out
of that איסור עשה? issur asei? That's sort of the point. If
you look in רש"י Rashi במילתא קמייתא bemilta kamaisa and it didn't
need to write a לאו lav in כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, why
should כהן גדול Kohen Gadol have a more severe prohibition if everyone
has this איסור עשה issur asei anyway?
באו לאו בעשה ולא
תעשה.
ba lav
beasei velo taaseh.
Yes, we do, but I don't think
it's any answer.
Yes, I agree. Okay. אלא לא אפיקתיה ממיתה ואוקימתיה על עשה. ela
lo afikta mimita veukimta al asei. So maybe that the מיתת הבעל
mitat habaal does not take her out from מיתה, mita, that is
that his death would not release her from the
חיוב מיתת בית דין, chiyuv mitat bet din, that is even with
the death of a woman's husband if she as an אלמנה almanah
would remarry, she's no longer אשת איש eshet ish to be punished
by חנק chenek that she would be punished for adultery by חנק,
chenek, but it would still be an איסור עשה. issur asei. מידי
דהוה אפסולי המוקדשים, midi dehava apsulei hamukdashim, just like we see by
פסולי המוקדשים psulei hamukdashim דמעיקרא
אית בהו מעילה demikara it behu meilah at for animals which are
unable to be brought for sacrifice for a variety of reasons, so
initially there's a prohibition of מעילה, meilah, that is trespass of הקדש
hekdesh property using the animal in some way, ואסורי בגיזה ועבודה vaasuri
begiza vaavoda and they cannot be shorn and they cannot be used
to do work. So you can't shear the sheep that was הקדש
hekdesh and you can't make the ox that was הקדש hekdesh plow
and all sorts of things. פרקינהו ממעילה, prakinhu mimeilah, so פרקינהו prakinhu
if you release them from their הקדש, hekdesh, that is because of
the fact that מעילה... meilah... Under certain circumstances at least, violating the
prohibition of מעילה *meila* actually does remove the קדושה *kedusha* from this
animal under certain circumstances. So פרקינהו מעילה *parkinhu meila*, לית בהו בגיזה
ועבודה *leit behu bigiza va'avoda*, מעילה לית בהו בגיזה ועבודה אסירי *meila
leit behu bigiza va'avoda asirei*. So while at that point then there's
no more prohibition of מעילה *meila*, the prohibition to shear the animal
or to make it work would still remain.
So the blemish on the animal is compared to the death of
a husband?
Correct. That is, you had a כשר *kosher* animal, a healthy animal,
כשר *kosher* animal, and it was going to be a קרבן korban
*korban*, and then it got a מום קבוע *mum kavua*, in some
way the מום *mum* is irreparable damage caused to this animal. So
now the animal you do not violate מעילה *meila* by using it
in some way, like riding on it or
putting
your coat, right, but you still can't use it. You can't shear
it and you can't make it work, but you could put your
coat on it or ride the animal or something in a different
way.
If I can't, is
riding it not using it?
Riding it would count as מעילה *meila* and we said מעילה לית
בהו בגיזה ועבודה אסירי *meila leit behu bigiza va'avoda asirei*.
So what is עבודה *avoda*? עבודה *avoda* is not riding it?
עבודה *avoda* means like making it pull a plow or something, something
much more, pulling you, but it's not the same kind of thing.
I'm not sure we don't have to go into it now, but
it's anyway, so okay. אסירי *asirei*. אלא מדאמר קרא *ella m'd'amar kra*,
no, so we have a real פסוק Pasuk *pasuk*. אלא מדאמר קרא
פן ימות במלחמה ואיש אחר יקחנה *ella m'd'amar kra pen yamut bamilchama
v'ish acher yikachena*. The פסוק Pasuk *pasuk* talking about who is exempted
from going to war says a man who has just recently been
married within the first year, but
that's not נישואין *nisuin* though, let's just, אירוסין *erusin*.
That's just אירוסין *erusin*, which is what we're talking about here. Fine.
פן ימות במלחמה *pen yamut bamilchama*, perhaps he'll die at war, ואיש
אחר יקחנה *v'ish acher yikachena*, and we know that the word קח
*kach*, ויקח *v'yikach*, כי יקח איש אשה *ki yikach ish isha*, that
refers to marriage. Proof אגב אורחא *agav-orcha* that another man could marry
her if he dies in war.
Only from אירוסין *erusin*, not from נישואין *nisuin*.
How do you know from נישואין *nisuin*? Okay, so one second. So
that's at least the דרשה drasha *drasha* we have right now. מתקיף
לה la. רב ששת בריה דרב אידי *matkif lah Rav Sheshet breih
d'Rav Idi*. So רב ששת בריה דרב אידי *Rav Sheshet breih d'Rav
Idi* asks this קשיא *kasha* on this. אימא מן אחר יבם yavam,
*eima man acher yavam*. Maybe we should say it's not she's allowed
to remarry, maybe the only person she would be allowed to remarry
would be the יבם yavam, *yavam* who she has an obligation to
marry. This is one of the two pieces today that's going to
be very relevant to really deep questions about יבום Yibbum *yibum*. And
that this question of רב ששת *Rav Sheshet* is rejected. אמר רב
אשי Amar Rav Ashi, שתי תשובות בדבר *amar Rav Ashi shtei teshuvot
badavar*. There are two answers to your question. חדא דיבם לא איקרי
אחר *chada d'yavam lo ikrei acher*. The יבם yavam. *yavam* is not
called אחר *acher*, he's not called another person. This is a major
question about יבום Yibbum *yibum*. How much is the יבם yavam, *yavam*,
he's somehow a stand-in for his brother who's died, he's continuing the
previous relationship in some way. The רמב"ם *Rambam* strangely highlights the fact
that the כתובה *ketubah* in יבום Yibbum *yibum* goes על נכסי בעלה
הראשון *al nikhsei ba'ala harishon*. The רמב"ם *Rambam* puts that in the
first few הלכות halachos. *halakhot* in הלכות halachos. יבום Yibbum, וחליצה *Hilkhot
Yibum v'Chalitza*. So really interesting questions about how much when we talk
about יבום Yibbum *yibum* is it a new relationship or how much
is it a continuation of the previous relationship. So here at least
we see יבם yavam. לא איקרי אחר *yavam lo ikrei acher*. ועוד
כתיב ושנאה האיש האחרון *v'od ktiv v'saneha ha'ish ha'acharon*. In discussing divorce
the פסוק Pasuk *pasuk* says ושנאה האיש האחרון *v'saneha ha'ish ha'acharon*, the
woman's second husband also hates her and decides to divorce her. וכתב
לה vechatav la, ספר כריתות sefer kritut. *v'chatav lah sefer keritut* and
he writes her a גט get, *get*. או כי ימות האיש האחרון
*o ki yamut ha'ish ha'acharon*, or if that man dies, then there
is a prohibition that she go remarry her first husband. That's the
איסור issur? *issur* of מחזיר גרושתו *machzir grushato*. But in such a
case, it's proof האיש האחרון כי ימות האיש האחרון *ha'ish ha'acharon ki
yamut ha'ish ha'acharon* would allow her to remarry another man. And so
you can see obviously that it's not just גירושין *gerushin* that permits
her to remarry, but also death as well. והקיש מיתה לגירושין *v'hikish
mita l'gerushin*. In that פסוק Pasuk *pasuk* discussing מחזיר גרושתו *machzir grushato*,
the death of the husband is connected to גירושין *gerushin*. מה גירושין
שריא וגומר *ma gerushin sharya v'gomar*, just like גירושין *gerushin* permits her
to remarry and completes, that is totally severs a relationship, אף מיתה
שריא וגומר *af mita sharya v'gomar*. So too the death of the
husband also completes the severance and allows her to remarry whomever she
would want. Except of course if there were an obligation of יבום
Yibbum *yibum*, in which case she would have a special separate מצוה
*mitzvah* to remarry, to marry the יבם yavam *yavam*.
One of the interesting questions that comes up in the ראשונים Rishonim,
*Rishonim* is all of these questions about אליהו הנביא *Eliyahu HaNavi* who
didn't die and rose to heaven in a chariot. So what is
the status of אליהו *Eliyahu*'s wife? Is אליהו *Eliyahu*'s wife, is he
still married? That's a, or using it as a theoretical construct to
discuss the question of in a case where a person did not
die but also somehow is not still alive either.
אשת אליהו be allowed to remarry or would she have to wait
and all sorts of things. And the question is also what about
what about if a person died and came back to life? So
we have stories in תנ"ך Tanakh about people who die and come
back to life and of course we also know that we believe
in תחיית המתים Techiyat HaMeitim and modern medicine. What about even something
as simple as CPR where a person's heart has stopped and then
the heart has been able to restart? And this gets into the
questions of cardiac death and brain death and all sorts of other
things.
Do you think there are actually some people who would say that
now this woman can go marry somebody else?
There is, it's in the פתחי תשובה. Pitchei Teshuva. There is פתחי
תשובה Pitchei Teshuvas about it. Very, yeah. Okay, היבמה נקנית HaYevama Nikneit
and and the בן איש חי, Ben Ish Chai, the בן איש
חי Ben Ish Chai
has a תשובה Teshuva where he distinguishes between what he calls תחיית
המתים על ידי נס, Techiyat HaMeitim al yedei nes, like something that
would happen nowadays, which basically at its core really is something that's
not really a נס nes and it really is possible and it's
really medical, compared to תחיית המתים Techiyat HaMeitim in the time of
משיח, Mashiach, which is going to be something different and really above
nature.
Do you think they really, they actually say that this woman could
go remarry if the husband had cardiac death?
I think everyone tries to explain how that's not allowed. But the
point is that it's at least a הוה אמינא Havah Amina and
the question that they're dealing with. Okay, let's continue. והיבמה נקנית בביאה.
VeHayevama Nikneit beViah. The last clause of this first משנה Mishnah in
the מסכת, Masechet, we're going to get into the second משנה Mishnah
today as well. So the last clause was talking about יבמה. Yevama.
היבמה נקנית בביאה וקונה את עצמה בחליצה ובמיתת היבם. HaYevama Nikneit beViah
vekonah et atzmah bechalitzah uv'mitat haYavam. בביאה מנלן? BeViah minalan?
So how do I know that a יבמה Yevama could be married
by ביאה? Biah? And now the question here if you look in
רש"י Rashi is not actually or not רש"י, Rashi, sorry, one of
the other ראשונים, Rishonim is not we're not actually asking how do
you know that יבמה Yevama could get married through ביאה, Biah, it's
actually how do we know that שטר Shtar and כסף Kesef don't
work? The only thing that works for יבמה Yevama is ביאה. Biah.
So בביאה מנלן? beViah minalan? אמר קרא יבמה יבא עליה ולקחה לו
לאשה. Amar kra Yevamah yavo aleha ulekachah lo le'ishah.
The פסוק Pasuk says her brother-in-law will יבא עליה, yavo aleha, יבא
עליה yavo aleha we know is the תורה's Torah's euphemism for a
sexual encounter, ולקחה לו לאשה ulekachah lo le'ishah and he'll take her
to him as a woman. ואימא לכולי מילתא כאישה? Veima lekulei milta
ke'ishah?
So maybe I'll say that she is equivalent to a woman in
every way? לא סלקא דעתך דתניא La salka daitach de'tanya meaning what?
Meaning that שטר Shtar and כסף Kesef should work? Exactly. Look in
רש"י, Rashi, ודלמא כאישה מה אישה כסף ושטר כביאה אף יבמה כסף
ושטר כביאה. ve'dilma ke'ishah, mah ishah kesef ushtar ke'viah, af yevamah kesef
ushtar ke'viah.
So כסף Kesef and שטר Shtar should be comparable to ביאה? Biah?
דהא כתיב לאשה? Daha ktiv le'ishah? So because it says ולקחה לו
לאשה ulekachah lo le'ishah and she'll be his wife, and that's why
you have to have a special לימוד limmud to exclude כסף Kesef
and שטר. Shtar. כי השתא סלקא דעתך דתניא יכול יהו בכסף ושטר
גומרין בה כדרך שהביאה גומרת בה? Ki hashata salka daitach de'tanya yakhol
yehu bekesef ushtar gomerin bah kederakh shehabiah gomeret bah? You might have
thought that כסף Kesef and שטר Shtar can complete, that is seal
seal the relationship to its fullest extent just like ביאה Biah does?
תלמוד לומר ויבמה. Talmud lomar veyibmah. The פסוק Pasuk is repetitive. The
פסוק pasuk says יבמה יבא עליה ולקחה לו לאשה, Yevamah yavo aleha
ulekachah lo le'ishah, her
brother-in-law will have a sexual encounter with her and take her as
his wife, ויבמה, veyibmah, and perform יבום Yibbum with her. So what
does that extra word ויבמה veyibmah mean? ביאה גומרת בה ואין כסף
ושטר גומרין בה. Biah gomeret bah ve'ein kesef ushtar gomerin bah. ביאה
Biah is the only mechanism that would work, but not כסף Kesef
and שטר. Shtar. So that's the difference, an important fundamental difference between
יבום Yibbum and and marriage קידושין, Kiddushin, is that the processes are
different but also because they're totally different חלות, chalos, like like I
was saying just before, the יבום Yibbum, is predicated on a pre-existing
relationship. It's a very different kind of relationship than קידושין Kiddushin where
you're taking two people who have no previous connection and bringing them
together. כדרך שהביאה גומרת בה תלמוד לומר ויבמה. Kederakh shehabiah gomeret bah
talmud lomar veyibmah. ביאה גומרת בה ואין כסף ושטר גומרין בה. Biah
gomeret bah ve'ein kesef ushtar gomerin bah. ואימא מאי ויבמה דבעל כרחה
מיבם? Ve'eima mai veyibmah debaal karkhah meyavem? Maybe we need the word
ויבמה veyibmah to learn that יבום, yibbum we do need the word
ויבמה veyibmah to learn that יבום yibbum can be performed בעל כרחה,
baal karkhah, that's against the woman's consent, or really without the woman's
explicit consent at this time? That is, her initial דעת daat for
קידושין Kiddushin includes in it a legal understanding of the fact that
should her husband die now, she is also implicitly agreeing to יבום
yibbum with her brother-in-law as well. אם כן לימא קרא ויבם מאי
ויבמה שמע מינה תרתי. Im ken leima kra veyabem? Mai veyibmah shma
mina tartei. So the פסוק pasuk has an extra ה heh meaning
all of this is redundant anyway, so the redundant redundancy we can
use to learn both both principles. That is, number one, יבום yibbum
is only by ביאה Biah and not כסף Kesef and שטר, Shtar,
and יבום yibbum could be בעל כרחה baal karkhah and we see
that those are very defining qualities about יבום, yibbum very different than
קידושין. Kiddushin.
Is there something about, is there this general principle, that is to
say you have a redundancy you say it teaches you x, there's
a קושיא kasha that says why maybe you need it for y
and then the hermeneutic response is שמע מינה תרתי shma mina tartei
you can learn both.
There
are always two ways there are two standard ways of resolving any
one of these. Thank you so much. One of the answers solutions
is well he who makes that דרשה drasha doesn't hold by this
other principle or he learns that from another פסוק pasuk or something
like that and it always has to be he ends up using
this פסוק pasuk for two
things.
Sometimes,
but this redundancy, remember, it could have said
ויבם, v'yibem, so the fact that it says ויבמה v'yibmah is two
redundancies.
Okay, so you have to say that all over again. Yeah, what
did you say about when she was... did you say when she
was accepting marriage she was accepting?
Right, that is the halakhic understanding of the דעת, da'at, that is
the woman's consent to the marriage, at least in some sense, considers
the consent that she gives at the initial marriage to include a
legal consent for יבום yibum that could arise later. Well, no, but
it's to say that the בעל כרחה ba'al karchah is because she
already implicitly consented to this relationship previously by marrying the
brother. But she knows the הלכה. halakhah. So she knows that should
her husband die and they don't have any children, she will be
obligated to either have יבום yibum? or חליצה chalitzah with this יבם,
yavam and therefore she is understood to have implicitly consented. Now obviously
we can get into and talk maybe later about how much יבום
yibum is בעל כרחה ba'al karchah or not, how much is the
woman's voice available to actually choose יבום yibum, or חליצה, chalitzah, and
how did חז"ל Chazal and the ראשונים Rishonim struggle with that question
particularly around the question whether or not we do יבום yibum anymore?
Is the סוגיא sugya in the first פרק perek in יבמות, Yevamot,
comes up in בכורות, Bechorot, so we'll get there in a few
years and all sorts of good things as well. Okay, so בכורות,
Bechorot, first פרק, perek, and then יבמות... Yevamot... what about חליצה? chalitzah?
How do I know that חליצה? chalitzah? Now the גמרא Gemara says
מנלן? minalan? Of course, the פסוק pasuk is explicit that there is,
there are several פסוקים pesukim in the תורה Torah dedicated to the
חליצה chalitzah ceremony. The גמרא's Gemara question מנלן minalan is how do
I know that יבמה קונה את עצמה בחליצה? yevamah koneh et atzmah
b'chalitzah? If you look in רש"י, Rashi, the רש"י Rashi says מנלן
דחלוצה מותרת להנשא? minalan d'chalutzah muteret lehinnase? How do I know that
a woman who has gone through the חליצה chalitzah process is allowed
to remarry? Maybe you'll just think after חליצה chalitzah she's still unable
to remarry anyone; she's rejected or been rejected by the יבם, yavam
but that doesn't mean that she would be permitted to marry someone
else.
Up to
a certain extent, yes, that is, the death of her first husband
left some strings attached; in this case, she has to resolve something
with the יבם. yavam Her choices were either יבום with the יבם,
yavam which would be marrying him, or חליצה chalitzah with the יבם.
yavam, And then how do we know that if she does חליצה
chalitzah she could go marry someone else, maybe she's still prohibited from
marrying anyone? So the גמרא Gemara says מנלן דכתיב ונקרא שמו בישראל
בית חלוץ הנעל. minalan dichtiv v'nikra shemo b'yisrael beit chalutz hana'al. The
יבם's yavam. name will be called the house of him whose shoe
was removed, which was very embarrassing. כיון שחלץ בה נעל הותרה לכל
ישראל. keivan shechalatz bah na'al hutra l'chol yisrael. Because the פסוק pasuk
says שמו בישראל, shemo b'yisrael, the יבם yavam will be known as
one whose shoe was removed, that means once she removes the shoe,
then she is allowed to remarry כל ישראל. kol yisrael. Now כל
ישראל kol yisrael obviously she would not be allowed to marry a
כהן; Kohen; it's interesting the question of the איסור חלוצה לכהן, issur
chalutzah l'kohen, a חלוצה chalutzah to marry a כהן Kohen is not
so simple that that's the same as a גרושה, gerushah, and in
fact I think most if not all the ראשונים think that חלוצה
לכהן chalutzah l'kohen is only a דרבנן d'rabbanan prohibition. That is, חליצה
chalitzah looks kind of like divorce but it's not the same.
Yes, it's also not permitted to the late husband's relatives.
Well, certain relatives, yes, and many of his relatives, right, especially, you
know, the other brother, once she does חליצה, chalitzah, right, the other
brothers. Okay, so הותרה לכל ישראל. hutra l'chol yisrael. האי ישראל להכי
הוא דאתא? hai yisrael l'hachi hu de'ata? Is that why the פסוק
pasuk says the word ישראל? Yisrael? האי מיבעי ליה לכדתניא רב שמואל
בר יהודה בישראל בבית דין של ישראל ולא בבית דין של עובדי
כוכבים, hai miba'ei lei l'kid'tanya Rav Shmuel bar Yehudah b'yisrael b'beity din
shel yisrael v'lo b'beity din shel ovdei kochavim, or perhaps בית דין
של גרים. beit din shel gerim. That is, so רב שמואל בר
יהודה Rav Shmuel bar Yehudah needs the word ישראל Yisrael to learn
not this principle that she would be allowed to remarry, which is
the whole problem that we're trying to derive about חליצה, chalitzah, he
needs that to learn the principle that חליצה chalitzah could only be
performed in front of a בית דין של ישראל, beit din shel
yisrael, a Jewish court, and not either perhaps a non-Jewish court, which
would be a very strange alternative, perhaps a
different גירסא girsa of this גמרא, Gemara, if you look in the
הגהות הב"ח, Hagahot HaBach, he says בית דין של גרים. beit din
shel gerim. We know that one of the limitations on converts is
under certain circumstances for certain kinds of cases converts can't serve as
judges or at least can only serve as judges for other converts,
and therefore this
may be according to at least רב שמואל בר יהודה's Rav Shmuel
bar Yehudah position one of those types of legal cases, that is,
how much is the חליצה chalitzah process a legal court kind of
process, how much is it that the דיינים dayanim who are there
for the חליצה chalitzah are sort of just witnessing the ceremony, so
sort of what's the cutoff or what's the formal standard in terms
of who those דיינים dayanim are. Yeah, it's interesting if you say
it's a בית דין של גרים beit din shel gerim and not
a בית דין של ישראל beit din shel yisrael then it implies
that or anything else.
Right, right,
that גרים geirim could serve exactly, and for most kinds of ממונות
mamonos cases, there are at least, yeah.
It's interesting that applying the term נכרים nochrim to גרים geirim is...
well, it's again, it's complicated, it really the גירסא girsa at some
point got mixed up and switched, so it's complicated, but yeah, part
of it has to do with exactly this question: what are we
talking about? Why the הוה אמינא hava amina of, oh, you could
go do חליצה chalitzah in a non-Jewish court is a very interesting
הוה אמינא. hava amina. I just remember seeing a תשובה teshuva of
Rav Kook a few weeks ago, where Rav Kook was dealing with
an עגונה agunah case and he made the very radical suggestion that
at least
מדאורייתא mi'd'Oraisa level, a civil divorce might count as a גט, get,
that is, it would be a גט פסול, get pasul, and he
used that as one סניף להקל snif l'hakeil in his whole דיון
diyun about how to deal with that עגונה agunah case. So very
interesting to think about what kinds of, particularly in marital law, you
know, the other major question in עגונה agunah questions is how much
is civil marriage or common-law marriage to be considered marriage as well,
if it's performed in the non-Jewish system. Okay, so לכדתני li'ked'tany Rav
Shmuel bar Yehuda: בישראל בבית דין של ישראל ולא בבית דין של
עובדי כוכבים. B'Yisroel b'beis din shel Yisroel v'lo b'beis din shel ovdei
kochavim. תרי בישראל כתיבי. Trei b'Yisroel kesivi. No, in the פרשה parsha
of חליצה, chalitzah, the word ישראל Yisroel comes up twice and we
could learn both הלכות. halachot ואחת מיבעי ליה לכדתניא: V'achas mibayei lei
li'ke'detanya: אמר רבי יהודה פעם אחת היינו יושבים לפני רבי טרפון ובאת
היבמה לחלוץ ואמר לנו ענו כולכם ואמרו חלוץ הנעל חלוץ הנעל. Amar
Rabbi Yehuda: Pa'am achas hayinu yoshvim lifnei Rabbi Tarfon u'va'as hayevama lachlotz,
v'amar lanu, anu kulchem v'imru chalotz hana'al, chalotz hana'al. So no, I
need one of those ישראל Yisroels to learn the story of what
happened with Rabbi Yehuda when Rabbi Yehuda went to Rabbi Tarfon. It's
interesting, Rabbi Tarfon is probably from בית שמאי, Beis Shammai, so it's
interesting to see some of the differences, Rabbi Tarfon and Rabbi Akiva
get into a lot of fights about a lot of different הלכה.
halacha. Rabbi Tarfon has some interesting שיטות, shittos, but here at least
Rabbi Yehuda went to Rabbi Tarfon and there was a יבמה yevama
who came in front of the בית דין beis din to do
her חליצה chalitzah and Rabbi Tarfon told us, that is all of
the judges, to say חלוץ הנעל חלוץ הנעל. chalotz hana'al, chalotz hana'al.
That is, once she removes the shoe from the יבם's yavam. foot,
then everyone else should actually call him חלוץ הנעל. chalotz hana'al. That
is, how much is the חלוץ הנעל, chalotz hana'al, how much is
it that it should be when we say ונקרא שמו בישראל בית
חלוץ הנעל, v'nikra shemo b'Yisroel beis chalotz hana'al, is that figurative, like
he will be known as someone who performed חליצה, chalitzah, or very
much is it you actually have to call him חלוץ הנעל chalotz
hana'al right now to his face? Okay, and the response to Rabbi
Yehuda or to this ברייתא braisa of Rabbi Yehuda is ההוא מונקרא
שמו נפקא. hahu m'v'nikra shemo nafa'ka. No, that could be learned out
from the word ונקרא שמו v'nikra shemo and not from the word
ישראל. Yisroel. And therefore we could learn all three הלכות. halachot. That
is, number one, we can learn that the court for חליצה chalitzah
perhaps cannot or the court for חליצה chalitzah cannot be a בית
דין beis din of עובדי כוכבים. ovdei kochavim. The court, number two,
that she would be allowed to remarry after חליצה. chalitzah. And number
three, that once the חליצה chalitzah is performed, the court has to
call him חלוץ הנעל חלוץ הנעל. chalotz hana'al, chalotz hana'al. Okay, ומיתת
היבם. u'mitas hayavam. Now what if the first, a woman's husband dies
and they have no children? So now she is זקוקה ליבום, zikuka
l'yibum, she has an obligation to perform יבום and her deceased husband
has one brother, and then that brother dies. The יבם yavam dies.
So the משנה mishna told us that at that point she is
permitted to remarry. So מנלן, minalan, how do we know this? קל
וחומר. kal v'chomer. We have it from a קל וחומר kal v'chomer
from אשת איש. eishes ish. מה אשת איש שהיא בחנק מיתת הבעל
מתירתה. Mah eishes ish she'hi b'chenek mitas habaal matirtah. So just like
an אשת איש eishes ish that is a regular married woman, if
her husband dies, and the prohibition, the punishment for אשת איש eishes
ish is חנק, chenek, it's a capital crime, and the death of
her husband permits her to remarry, יבמה שהיא בלאו, yevama she'hi b'lav,
a
יבמה yevama whose prohibition is only punishable by lashes is a regular
לאו, lav, לא כל שכן, lo kol she'ken, shouldn't she be allowed
to remarry with the death of her יבם yavam as well? So
we have to now, we're going to go through, perhaps some of
these קל וחומרים kal v'chomers are going to get rejected. מה לאשת
איש שכן יוצאה בגט. Ma l'eishes ish she'ken yotza b'get. אשת איש
eishes ish is different from יבמה yevama because she can be divorced
with a גט, get, and we know that a יבמה yevama cannot
be released with a גט, get? she has to have חליצה. chalitzah.
תאמר בזו שאינה יוצאה בגט. Tomar b'zo she'eina yotza b'get. Can you
make a comparison between the two cases because of the difference regarding
the גט? get, הא נמי יוצאה בחליצה. Ha nami yotza b'chalitzah. No,
so maybe we'll say even though she can't be released with a
גט, get she could be released by חליצה. chalitzah. And so perhaps
there is an equation, at least a partial equation, between גט get.
and חליצה. chalitzah. אלא מה לאשת איש שכן אוסרה מתירה. Ela ma
l'eishes ish she'ken oserah matirah. In the case of אשת איש, eishes
ish, אוסרה מתירה. oserah matirah. The one who made her prohibited, that
is her husband, is the one who releases her, that is either
through the process of his own death or the process of giving
the גט. get, So can that be compared to יבום? And now
the הוה אמינא hava amina here is going to be rejected. The
הוה אמינא hava amina is that יבום is different. Why? In יבום,
who's the one who releases her? Well... The יבם, yavam he does
חליצה. chalitzah. Who's the one who created the איסור? issur, The assumption
is that the deceased husband is the one who created the איסור,
issur? and אמר רב אשי, הא נמי אוסרה ומטירה. ha nami osra
u'matira. No, Rav Ashi says, actually both roles are played by the
יבם. yavam The question is, who is the one who creates the
איסור? issur Is the איסור issur created by the deceased husband or
is the איסור issur. created by the יבם yavam himself?
Or the existence of the יבם.
Exactly. Because we can see here, and Rav Ashi explains to us
now, יבם אוסרה. yavam osra. The יבם is the one who creates
the איסור. So יבם
שרי לה. yavam sharei lah. The יבם is the one who releases
her. Why? How is it that the יבם creates the prohibition? Because
if he were not there, if there were no brothers, then she
would be allowed to remarry immediately. So the existence of the יבם
is what creates the prohibition of יבמה לשוק yevamah lashuk and not
the husband. Because the death of the husband creates an obligation for
יבום if and only if there is a brother.
ותהא אשת איש יוצאה בחליצה, Vetehei eishet ish yotza bechalitzah, could we
say that a married woman, that is a regular wife, would be
allowed to be divorced by חליצה, chalitzah, מקל וחומר? mikal vachomer? Can
we learn it the opposite direction? Now we're not trying to learn
divorce to חליצה, chalitzah,
we're trying to learn חליצה chalitzah to divorce. ומה יבמה שאינה יוצאה
בגט יוצאה בחליצה, Umah yevamah she-eina yotza beget yotza bechalitzah, a יבמה
yevamah cannot be divorced by a גט, get, but she could be
released with חליצה. chalitzah. זו שיוצאה בגט, Zo she-yotza beget, אינו דין
שיוצאה בחליצה? eino din she-yotza bechalitzah? Couldn't we make this קל וחומר
kal vachomer and say, ah, so an אשת איש eishet ish who
is released by גט, get, obviously could be released by חליצה chalitzah
as well? Sounds like חליצה chalitzah is stronger. Now we know the
answer, right? אמר קרא, Amar kra, ספר כריתות. ספר כורתה ואין דבר
אחר כורתה. Sefer kortah ve-ein davar acher kortah. It could only be
through a written document that creates the divorce. That is, a married
woman, אשת איש, eishet ish, can only be divorced with a written
document. And a יבמה yevamah is released not by a גט, get
but by חליצה, chalitzah, which is an embodied process. So it's very
different types of activities that are involved. Also to consider just the
fact we already saw even in this שקלא וטריא shakla vetarya here,
the prohibition of חליצה, chalitzah, that חליצה chalitzah is undoing is a
much lower level prohibition. So also you should say, you should have
a logical problem with this קל וחומר kal vachomer as well. ותהא
יבמה יוצאה בגט, Vetehei yevamah yotza beget, מקל וחומר, mikal vachomer, couldn't
we say יבמה yevamah could be released with a גט get. מקל
וחומר? mikal vachomer? מה אשת איש שאינה יוצאה בחליצה יוצאה בגט, Mah
eishet ish she-eina yotza bechalitzah yotza beget, an אשת איש eishet ish
is not released with חליצה, chalitzah, she can be divorced with a
גט. get זו שיוצאה בחליצה, Zo she-yotza bechalitzah, אינו דין שיוצאה בגט?
eino din she-yotza beget? Couldn't a woman who is released with חליצה
chalitzah be released with a גט get as well? אמר קרא, Amar
kra, ככה. kacha. So by the הלכות halachot. of חליצה, chalitzah, the
word the Torah used the word ככה, kacha, which is ככה יעשה
לאיש אשר לא יבנה את בית אחיו. kacha ye-aseh la-ish asher lo
yivneh et beit achiv.
Interesting echoes in the מגילה, Megillah, we have ככה יעשה לאיש אשר
המלך חפץ ביקרו. kacha ye-aseh la-ish asher hamelech chafetz bikaro. So just
always, you know, you're reading the כי תצא Ki Tetze and you
hear ככה יעשה לאיש. kacha ye-aseh la-ish. Okay, וככה עיכובא. v'kacha ikuva.
So the word ככה kacha comes to hold back, that is to
create a limitation in terms of the application of those הלכות. halachot
Okay. וכל היכא דאיכא עיכובא לא דרשינן קל וחומר? Vechol heicha de-ika
ikuva lo darshinan kal vachomer? Is it really true that whenever we
have an עיכובא, ikuva, that is some other part of the דרשה
drasha that's making a restriction, that we still wouldn't be able to
make any קל וחומר? kal vachomer? והא יום הכפורים דכתיב גורל וחוקה.
Veha Yom HaKippurim de-chtiv goral ve-chukkah. So יום הכפורים Yom Kippurim has
two principles. Number one, the גורל, goral, that is we have the
two goats, and one of them is going to be a קרבן
חטאת korban chatat and one of them is going to go to
the desert to be pushed off of the cliff. And the Torah
used the word חוקה. chukkah. חוקה, Chukkah, we know, is a term
of precise legal application from the word חוק. chok. So בחוקה, be-chukkah,
so it should be a limitation. That is, we shouldn't extend or
reapply those הלכות. ותניא ועשהו חטאת הגורל עושה חטאת ואין השם עושה
חטאת. Vetanya ve-asahu chatat hagoral oseh chatat ve-ein hashem oseh chatat. So
the הלכה halacha regarding the גורל goral is that with the two
goats of יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, only the גורל goral can designate
which of the two goats is going to be a קרבן חטאת
korban chatat and which not. And not קריאת שם, kriyat shem, that
is actually just putting your hands on the קרבן and saying this
is a חטאת לה' chatat l'Hashem or something like that. On יום
כיפור, Yom Kippur, the only way to designate the goats is using
the גורל. goral. And that's from the
פסוק pasuk
ועשהו חטאת, v'asahu chatat, שיכול והלא דין הוא. she-yachol vehalo din hu.
So what? Couldn't we make a קל וחומר? kal vachomer? ומה במקום
שלא קידש הגורל קידש השם, Umah bimkom shelo kidesh hagoral kidesh hashem,
even in a place where the גורל goral does not work, that
is some other set of קרבנות, korbanot, for example, if you bring
a קן, ken, you bring two birds, one is an עולה olah
and one is a חטאת, chatat, and you've brought the two birds
together and you haven't yet designated them. So if you bring the
קן ken and you say, the only way now to designate which
one is an עולה olah and which one is a חטאת chatat
is by actually telling, announcing it to the birds.
So a גורל goral would not work. מקום שקידש הגורל אינו דין
שקידש השם? Makom shekidesh hagoral eino din shekidesh hashem? So if the
גורל goral is a weaker mechanism than קריאת שם, kriyat shem, so
maybe גורל goral should also work if גורל goral works on יום
כיפור. Yom Kippur. then also קריאת שם kriyat shem should work on
יום כיפור Yom Kippur as well. תלמוד לומר ועשהו חטאת, Talmud lomar
v'asahu chata'at, הגורל עושה חטאת ואין השם עושה חטאת. Hagoral oseh chata'at
ve-ein hashem oseh chata'at. And that's why the פסוק pasuk needs a
special limitation to exclude that קל וחומר kal vachomer so that you
can't think that on יום כיפור Yom Kippur you could just do
קריאת שם. kriyat shem. But that means even in a case where
we have the פסוק pasuk uses the word חוקה, chukka, which is
a limitation, which we would think you shouldn't be able to make
a קל וחומר, kal vachomer, we still had a הוה אמינא hava
amina based on a קל וחומר kal vachomer that had to be
rejected by a פסוק pasuk, anyway. So בטעמא
דמייתי קרא הא לאו הכי דרשינן קל וחומר, betama d'maitei kra ha
lav hachi darshinan kal vachomer, if it weren't for the fact that
the פסוק pasuk had excluded it we would have made this קל
וחומר kal vachomer אף גב דכתיב ביה חוקה, af gav d'chtiv bei
chukka, even though the פסוק pasuk says חוקה. chukka. אמר קרא לה
לה ולא ליבמה. amar kra la la v'lo l'yevama.
So the פסוק pasuk. regarding divorce says לה. la That is regarding
ונתן venatan ונתן כי יקח איש אשה ובעלה ושנאה ונתן כסף ספר
כריתות ונתן בידה ושלחה מביתו. venatan ki yikach ish isha u've'alah usne'ah
venatan kesef sefer kritut venatan beyada veshilcha mibeito.
I'm forgetting where the word לה la comes in the פסוק, pasuk
but
וכתב לה, vechatav la, right? Sorry, you spent three months on מסכת
גיטין Masechet Gittin and you forget. Okay, so אמר קרא לה. amar
kra la. So the פסוק pasuk regarding divorce says וכתב לה, la.
the husband has to write it for her, לה ולא ליבמה, la
v'lo l'yevama, only for his wife but not for a יבמה. yevama.
That's the פסוק pasuk that comes to exclude. That is, we would
have thought that because it said ככה kacha it comes to exclude
a קל וחומר, kal vachomer, so fine, even if you say that
it excludes the קל וחומר, kal vachomer, we need to learn—we don't
say that because we had this whole thing about יום כיפור, Yom
Kippur, and therefore instead we need this explicit פסוק. pasuk That is,
the word לה la says לה ולא ליבמה. la v'lo l'yevama.
So the חכמים Chachamim in this סוגיא sugya are working really hard
to maintain
the primacy or the hegemony of פסוקים psukim over קל וחומר. kal
vachomer. קל וחומר kal vachomer is very powerful source for learning הלכה.
halacha.
And nonetheless we want to avoid it.
Right, but they have to work really hard to
defend
the פסוקים psukim over the human mind.
Correct. And we had that a few days ago as well in
even just comparing all the different mechanisms of קידושין kiddushin as well
and many קל וחומר kal vachomers were rejected based on פסוקים. psukim.
And I think an important part of this discussion is to say
קל וחומר kal vachomer is based on a logical analogy. That is,
these two cases are basically the same and we can make extrapolations
and comparisons between them. What חז"ל Chazal are telling us here using
these פסוקים psukim and the unique aspects of each of these different
processes is to say ייבום Yibbum is different from marriage. Marriage is
different from אמה עבריה. amah ivriyah. The three different types of marriage
are certainly in some ways different from each other and you can't
just draw analogies between them and you can't just compare them because
they actually are unique and distinct in their own ways. It's important
to think then, especially part of the problem, especially from a modern
perspective of the first פרק perek of קידושין Kiddushin is that so
much of the structure places marital relationships in a context of קניינים
kinyanim and purchase. We're going to get to the משנה mishna about
עבד עברי eved ivri today. So that question raises a serious question
about how do we think about marriage, and the answer is חז"ל
Chazal are very attuned to the fact that each of these is
actually a very distinct process that just happens to use sometimes the
same words or similar ideas but are actually very different. Okay. So
don't we say, you should have asked me a question, right? The
word לה. la So אימא לה לשמה, eima la lishma, don't we
need the word לה la, to learn that the גט get? has
to be written
לשמה? lishma? תרי לה כתיבי. trei la ktivi. No, the word לה
appears twice, so it's fine. וחד מיבעי ליה חד לה לשמה ואידך
לה ולא לה ולחברתה? ve'chad mibei lei chad la lishma v'idach la
v'lo la u'l'chavertah?
Don't I need the second לה, not to learn that it's לה
ולא ליבמה la v'lo l'yevama but it's לה ולא לה ולחברתה, la
v'lo la u'l'chavertah, that is, a man cannot divorce his two wives
with the same גט? get, Okay. אלא אמר קרא נעל נעל. ella
amar kra naal naal. No, we learn it from the פרשה parsha
of חליצה chalitza actually. To learn that a יבמה yevama cannot be
divorced with a גט, we learn from חליצה, chalitza, that is נעל.
נעל אין מידי אחרינא לא.
naal naal in midi achrina
lo. So she can only be released by the shoe and not
anything else. Very interesting. Just like we have a דרשה drasha ספר
כורתה ואין דבר אחר כורתה sefer kortah v'ein davar acher kortah by
divorce, by חליצה chalitza we also have נעל naal. נעל אין מידי
אחרינא לא. naal in midi achrina lo. Very similar kind of דרשות,
drashot, that is, the precise formulation in the תורה, Torah, either a
written document or a shoe, plays the role and nothing else can
play the role. Okay. והאי נעל להכי הוא דאתא? v'hai naal l'hachi
hu d'ata? So is that really what the word נעל naal comes
to teach? האי מיבעי ליה לכדתניא נעל נעלו אין אין לי אלא
נעלו? hai mibei lei l'chid'tanya naal na'alo in ein li ela na'alo?
The word נעלו na'alo would say I would have thought only his
shoe. The fact that it said נעל, naal, נעל של כל אדם.
naal shel kol adam. So, sorry, נעל של כל אדם מנה לן?
naal shel kol adam minalan? How do I know you could use
anyone's shoe? That is, the יבם does not need to own the
shoe. That is, it's a symbolic process and it's not actually her
removing his shoe, but someone can loan him a shoe, he can
take the shoe from the בית דין, beit din, whatever, it doesn't
have to be his shoe.
Only a communal sandal that they used to use.
Right, so that's what they use now. It has to be—and we're
going to see some of the requirements of the חליצה chalitza shoe.
So מנה לן? minalan? תלמוד לומר נעל נעל ריבה. Talmud lomar naal
naal riba. So the word נעל naal comes as an expansive notion
of a shoe, therefore it could be anyone's shoe, it's not
נעל. naal. It has to be a shoe that is suitable for
him and we're going to see פרט לגדול שאין יכול להלך בו.
Prat legadol she'ein yachol lehalech bo. It cannot be too large for
him to walk in, you know if you have big clown shoes
on, it would be very difficult to walk around, your foot is
flopping around, so that wouldn't work. Okay, and פרט לקטן שאינו חופה
רוב רגלו. Prat lekatan she'eino chofet rov raglo. And it excludes a
shoe that is too small that does not cover the majority of
his foot. Now, I would think even a shoe that covers the
majority of my foot is probably too small. But that's an interesting
definition. How much is this a legal problem of, you know, רובו
ככולו Rubo kekulo and how much is this a physical problem of
the shoe fitting on your foot or not? Because I would think
even a size ten foot wearing a size eight shoe is going
to be very uncomfortable even though it covers the רוב. rov. Now
they had a different kind of a shoe obviously, it's more of
like a sandal, but still. Okay. And we have another exclusion, not
just not too big and not too small, but also
פרט למסוליא שאין לו עקב. Prat lemesulim she'ein lo akeiv. Also certain
kinds of sandals that do not have a heel. Presumably this is
referring to the back of the shoe, there's a picture there in
the
Steinsaltz. Basically flip flops. Flip flops don't have a cup for the
heel to sit in the shoe, and therefore that's one of the
exclusions. It has to be נעלו הראוי לו. Naalo hara'uy lo. Seemingly
that flip flops are not ראוי לו. ra'uy lo. That is they're
not real shoes in any real sense. אם כן נכתוב קרא נעל.
Im kein nechtov kra naal. So then the Torah could have just
said naal. מאי הנעל? Mai hanaal? שמע מינה תרתי. Shema mina tartei.
We can learn two things. That is number one, a יבמה yevama
could only be released by חליצה chalitza and no other way. And
number two, we learn all the exclusions for the physical object of
the shoe discussed at length in מסכת יבמות. Masechet Yevamot. We have
the next משנה. mishna. And we have about twenty minutes so hopefully
we'll be able to make some headway in this סוגיא. sugya. This
is a discussion of עבד עברי. Eved Ivri. We are changing gears
for now, we're going to come back to קידושין Kiddushin soon. Don't
worry. The גמרא Gemara can't keep itself away from its main topic
obviously. But עבד עברי Eved Ivri we know, at least in the
Torah, appears seemingly three times. There's the beginning discussion in פרשת משפטים.
Parshat Mishpatim. There's a discussion in פרשת בהר. Parshat Behar. And there's
a discussion in
ספר דברים Sefer Devarim in
פרשת ראה, Parshat Re'eh, right? So each of those three sections has
different focus and different aspects of the עבד עברי. Eved Ivri. Some
of the Bible critics have suggested that that means that they must
be from different sources. I heard a very illuminating and interesting lecture
from Professor Aaron Koller at YU who spoke at length about how
really it's obvious from not only Jewish sources but also from the
Ancient Near East that actually all of those were very similar parts
of the legal code of slaves and they're totally compatible, they don't
contradict each other at all, and they're actually very clear to be
all part of a unified system. So it was actually very interesting
to study that at depth and he thinks that that's at least
one of the major problems with the modern biblical scholarship which is
that often they see something that they think is a contradiction and
they jump on it and won't look even more critically about the
other similar kinds of things in Ancient Near Eastern sources as well
as the תורה. Torah. There are two ways to become a slave,
that is עבד עברי, Eved Ivri, a slave of a citizen type.
That is, a Jewish person indentures himself for two reasons. One is
מוכר עצמו. Mocher atzmo. You need extra cash, you're very poor, you
indenture yourself to work as a servant for someone. Option number two
is מכרוהו בית דין. Mecharuhu Beis Din. If the בית דין Beis
Din sells a person as a slave and that would be in
a case where a person stole something and is so poor that
he cannot pay back the קרן. keren. Cannot pay back the principal
value. You steal a loaf of bread, you eat the whole loaf
of bread, and you have no money, you can't pay it back,
so you have to be indentured to pay off the debt. Or
you stole something even more valuable and then consumed it in such
a way that you couldn't pay it back. Now, the בית דין
Beis Din would not sell a person as a slave if they
could pay the קרן keren but would be unable to pay כפל.
keifel. That's because the כפל, keifel, the double payment that we pay
in cases of גניבה geneiva is an additional fine imposed. There's the
restitution and then there's the punishment. So the punishment you don't get
sold to pay back, but the קרן, keren, the principal value, you
do. The משנה mishna says: עבד עברי נקנה בכסף ובשטר. Eved Ivri
nikne bechesef uvishtar. An עבד עברי Eved Ivri could be purchased, but
not really purchased, obviously it's an indenture agreement, so that agreement could
be solidified and formalized either by כסף kesef or with a שטר,
shtar, with a bill. וקונה עצמו בשנים. Vekoneh atzmo beshanim. He becomes
freed from his indentured servitude, he acquires his own freedom בשנים, beshanim,
either with the passage of six years—and עבד עברי Eved Ivri works
only six years, right? The פסוק pasuk says, ועבדך שש שנים. Va'avadcha
sheish shanim. So the six years. וביובל, Uvayovel, or if the יובל
Yovel year comes even in the middle of those six
years. ובגרעון כסף, Uvigraon kesef, or in the paying off the debt,
that is the maximum term is six years, but if he stole
something that was relatively cheap, then the time will be shorter; and
also, if he has saved up money from somewhere else or someone
gives him a big gift of money, he can pay off the
rest of his debt. If he worked two months and paid off
50% and then someone gave him, he won the lottery and he
can pay back the rest, so then that's also גרעון כסף. geraon
kasef. You can reduce it with money. יתרה עליו אמה העבריה, yetera
alav ama haivria, and אמה העבריה, ama haivria, that is a young
woman, a girl who was indentured by her father. It's interesting to
note the one of the major questions about עבד עברי eved ivri
is it seems like an adult woman could not make herself an
עבד עברי. eved ivri. There's a process for adult men and there's
a process for minor girls, but there's nothing for boys and there's
nothing for women, interestingly.
So that's part of the question. So אמה העבריה שקונה את עצמה
בסימנים. ama haivria shekona et atzma bsimanim. אמה העבריה ama haivria when
she reaches physical maturity, she also is released from her indentured servitude.
הנרצע, hanirtza, if a slave
agrees to have his ear pierced, הנרצע, hanirtza, one whose ear was
pierced, נקנה ברציעה. nikna bretzia. That status is acquired through the piercing
of the ear. דקונה את עצמו ביובל ובמיתת האדון. dekone et atzmo
b’yovel u’vmitat ha’adon. And he goes free either at the יובל yovel
year or when his master dies. So the עבד נרצע eved nirtza
has some different הלכות we're going to see, but he- the point
is that he does not go free with the passage of six
years. That's the point. At the end of six years, he can
agree to become the נרצע nirtza and also he can't pay off
his debt. His debt could only be released by the יובל yovel
year or by the אדון. adon. Yes.
So if a- an adult- an adult
male becomes in debt. Yes. He can indenture his minor daughter to
work off the debt. Correct. But he can't indenture his minor son.
Correct.
Okay. And- and remember also one of the aspects of אמה העבריה
ama haivria is not only that it's an indentured servitude for this
young woman for a few years, it also carries with it the
potential or perhaps the hope that she'll be married off by her
אדון. adon. That is, the אדון adon could marry her or he
can marry her to his son, and that's called ייעוד. yiud. That's
going to come up and תוספות Tosafot mentioned that many times in
the earlier part of the פרק perek in the comparisons between אמה
העבריה ama haivria and marriage.
So from that perspective, in that context, it's actually a יתרון yitron
for that little girl- for that
young girl, as it were. The father is poor. Right. Here's an
opportunity for her to marry into a wealthy family.
Right, I mean. Exactly. And that- it really is, you know, you
think about it, on the one hand, we have an aversion to
discussions of child marriage and to servitude and slavery and child labor
laws,
hope for a
better- but it very much is. And that's exactly the tension between
the Torah's system, which obviously in a different cultural climate provided many
mechanisms to really help people, which nowadays we have a certain aversion
to. We have to see it with new eyes, I think. So
the גמרא Gemara says, עבד עברי נקנה בכסף. eved ivri nikna bchesef.
Yes.
So is there a parallel here to the person in a city
of refuge? Because of the מיתת הכהן גדול mitat hakohen gadol or
the יובל, yovel, so both of
these- it's very interesting parallel that I hadn't thought of that, but
that's really interesting point. There's a lot been discussed about why is
it that the death of the כהן גדול kohen gadol is a
process that releases the people in the רוצח. rotzeach. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says, עבד עברי נקנה בכסף מנלן? eved ivri nikna bchesef
minalan? מנלן? minalan? How do we know that an עבד עברי eved
ivri could be purchased with money? אמר קרא, amar kra, מכסף מקנתו,
mikasef miknato, מלמד שנקנה בכסף. melamed shenikna bchesef. So the פסוק pasuk.
in פרשת בהר Parshat Behar says, when a Jewish person was bought
as a slave by a non-Jew and he wants to buy back
his freedom, he needs a relative to bring money to pay off
the value. So מכסף מקנתו, mikasef miknato, that means he had been
bought with money. So we said, אשכחן עבד עברי הנמכר לעובד כוכבים,
הואיל וכל קנינו בכסף, נמכר לישראל מנלן? ashkechan eved ivri hanimkar l’oved
kochavim, ho’il v’chol kinyano b’chesef, nimkar l’yisrael minalan? So fine, I get
that for a Jewish person sold as a slave to a non-Jew,
it's obvious that you could use כסף kesef because all of a
non-Jew's purchases go by כסף. kesef. That is, the system of קנינים
kinyanim applies to non-Jews in a different way than it applies to
Jews, perhaps because of some of the underlying mechanisms rely more on
a belief in the Torah or belief in קדושת ישראל kedushat yisrael
in a different way than a very financial process. Some of them
are more about agreement and trust and making that agreement, different than
כסף, kesef, which is a very financial, monetary, just exchange of value.
So כסף kesef works for non-Jews. הואיל וכל קנינו בכסף. ho’il v’chol
kinyano b’chesef. So and also becomes an interesting הלכה למעשה halacha l’maaseh
question we said about פסח. Pesach. So when you do the מכירת
חמץ, mechirat chametz, when you're selling חמץ chametz to a non-Jew, there
are many different mechanisms that people try to employ לחומרא l’chumra to
make sure that it works. So they try to do lots of
different קנינים kinyanim just in case this one doesn't work for- for
this kind of thing. So anyway, עבד עברי הנמכר לעובד כוכבים, הואיל
וכל קנינו בכסף, eved ivri hanimkar l’oved kochavim, ho’il v’chol kinyano b’chesef,
נמכר לישראל מנלן? nimkar l’yisrael minalan? So how do we know about
in a case of נמכר לישראל, nimkar le'Yisrael, that is a Jewish
person indentures himself to a Jew, that it would work with money
as well? אמר קרא amar kra והפדה. vehifdah. That's in the פסוק
pasuk. talking about אמה העבריה amah ha'Ivriyah and והפדה, vehifdah, that is
something to do with her payment, payment of her freedom, so מלמד
שמגרעת פדיונה, melamed shemigerat pidyonah, she could reduce the פדיון, pidyon, פדיון
pidyon is like the redeem value. Interesting use of the word, it's
different than a price. פדיון pidyon is how much money you have
to pay back to go free. We talk about פדיון שבויים pidyon
shvuyim and things like that. ויצאה, veyatzah,
she can go free. אשכחן אמה העבריה. ashkechan amah ha'Ivriyah. So then
fine, the פסוק pasuk, told me about אמה העבריה. amah ha'Ivriyah. הואיל
ומקדשה בכסף, ho'il umkadsha bekesef, just like she could get married with
money, מקניה בכסף, maknya bekesef, she could also be indentured or purchased
through money. עבד עברי מנלן? eved Ivri menalan? So I still don't
know the prime case, that is עבד עברי, eved Ivri, the male
adult male Jewish servant. אמר קרא כי ימכר לך אחיך העברי. amar
kra ki yimacher lecha achicha ha'Ivri. No, we go back to the
פסוק now in דברים, Devarim, right? We've seen now we've had to
go to each of the different locations to find the פסוק. So
כי ימכר לך אחיך העברי, ki yimacher lecha achicha ha'Ivri, when your
Jewish brother is sold to
you, או העבריה, o ha'Ivriyah, ועבדך שש שנים. ve'avadcha sheish shanim. מקיש
עבד עברי לעבריה. makish eved Ivri le'Ivriyah. An adult man is connected
here to a minor Jewish woman. אשכחן מכרוהו בית דין. ashkechan macharuhu
Beis Din. So fine, now you've taught me about מכרוהו בית דין,
macharuhu Beis Din, a case where he was sold for having stolen
and needs to pay back the criminal, the theft. הואיל ונמכר בעל
כרחו, ho'il venimkar be'al korcho, he could be sold against his will
by the בית דין. Beis Din. מוכר עצמו מנלן? mocher atzmo menalan?
How do I know about the case of מוכר עצמו, mocher atzmo,
that is a person who just decides I'm too poor and decides
to indenture himself? יליף שכיר שכיר. yalif sachir sachir. We can learn
by a גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah of the word שכיר. sachir. The
word שכיר sachir appears in דברים Devarim where it's talking about purchase
using money for מכרוהו בית דין macharuhu Beis Din is also called
שכיר, sachir, and also the word שכיר sachir comes up in פרשת
בהר parshat Behar in talking about מוכר עצמו. mocher atzmo. הניחא למאן
דיליף שכיר שכיר. hanicha leman deyalif sachir sachir. So fine, that works
for someone who makes that גזירה שוה שכיר שכיר. gezeirah shavah sachir
sachir. אלא למאן דלא יליף שכיר שכיר, ella leman dela yalif sachir
sachir, what about the one who does not make the גזירה שוה?
gezeirah shavah? מאי איכא למימר? mai ika lemeimar? אמר קרא וכי תשיג,
amar kra vechi tassig, if his hand reaches, that is also in
פרשת בהר, parshat Behar, מוסיף על עניין ראשון. mosif al inyan rishon.
It adds an additional gloss onto the previous
discussion, וילמד עליון מתחתון, veyilmad elyon mitachton, and the upper case is
learned from the lower case. Now עליון מתחתון elyon mitachton meaning that
the two paragraphs in the same section are talking about the עבד
עברי eved Ivri and the one, the upper case was the case
we already saw before which was מכסף מקנתו mikesef miknaso talking about
a Jewish person sold to a non-Jew, and here now in the
same paragraph or nearby paragraph is a discussion about a Jew sold
to a Jew and therefore you could learn
עליון מתחתון.
elyon mitachton. זה כעין סמיכות פרשיות. zeh ke'ein semichut parshiyot.
It's kind of like a סמיכות פרשיות semichut parshiyot thing. I don't
think I've ever seen the לשון lashon עליון מתחתון elyon mitachton as
a strange formulation. It's interesting. Yeah, okay.
It's
kind of like a סמיכות פרשיות, semichut parshiyot, the proximity, contextual proximity.
It's looser than a real היקש, heikesh, but it's kind of close.
Again, it's in a broader set of paragraphs, the whole פרשת בהר
parshat Behar is about land and slaves and then, you know, paragraph
by paragraph, kind of, so it's an interesting point, right.
It's not a logical analogy; it's a literary principle, right.
That is, we have two paragraphs about Jewish people selling themselves as
slaves near each other, so we can learn from one to the
other, a kind of a loose היקש. heikesh. Okay. ומאן תנא דלא
יליף שכיר שכיר? uman Tanna dela yalif sachir sachir? Who is the
תנא Tanna who does not learn the גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah such
that he would need to use this kind of a היקש? heikesh?
האי תנא הוא דתניא המוכר עצמו נמכר לשש ויתר על שש. hai
Tanna hu detanya hamocher atzmo nimkar lesheish veyaser al sheish. So that's
the תנא Tanna who taught this ברייתא braisa which says: המוכר עצמו,
hamocher atzmo, a person sells himself into servitude, could sell himself for
שש sheish years or יתר על שש, yaser al sheish, more than
שש sheish years. Why? If you're entering into the agreement, you could
do whatever you want. You're basically just making a business arrangement, that
is, you go to this guy and say I want to work
for you, pay me this wage, and he says great and he
gives you the money. So I don't understand; you could do any
kind of hiring you want, more than שש sheish years.
מכרוהו בית דין אינו נמכר אלא לשש. macharuhu Beis Din eino nimkar
ella lesheish. The point is that when a בית דין Beis Din
has to sell someone who was a thief who is being sold
against his will for a crime, that's a case where the Torah
places a limit on it; it could only be שש sheish years.
This is not so true; we regulate other types of transactions. Fine.
So but this is one opinion in the תנאים. Tannaim. The other
תנאים Tannaim are going to reject and say look, עבד עברי eved
Ivri maximum is שש sheish years no matter what, and that has
an underlying value to teach us no person should be working as
an עבד עברי eved Ivri more than שש sheish years even if,
and again we have to think, עבד עברי eved Ivri isn't so
similar to what we would call slavery, but it has certain elements
that are similar. The Torah used the word עבד; eved; you're not
supposed to be an עבד, eved, you're supposed to be, you know,
your own free person. So there is exactly that question of values
there as well, and that question of regulation is, well, if it
were just a business arrangement the Torah wouldn't have as much of
a need to have regulated it so precisely, but if it really
has that
שמץ shmutz of.
For financial reasons, exactly.
Not just straight employment.
Right, it's something beyond employment because he does work and live in
the same place and he has certain things provided for him by
the אדון, Adon,
but it's close to employment, it's certainly a kind of
all-expenses-included kind of employment.
A law is a similar kind of thing, right? I mean... Right.
No, for sure. Meaning, right. But the regulations...
Of course.
And so that barrier is a bit more flexible. The point is
to see that מכרוהו בית דין mecharu beit din where it's done
against his will and it's done for a crime, the תורה Torah
specifically has to put a limit on it to say it can't
be more than six years, there's no punishment more than six years
for this kind of a crime.
Okay, and so the concept of being עבד השם. Eved Hashem. Exactly.
כי לי בני ישראל עבדים עבדי הם. Ki li b'nei Yisrael avadim
avadai hem. Right. עבדים ולא עבדים לעבדים. Avadim v'lo avadim l'avadim. Okay.
מכרוהו בית דין אינו נמכר אלא לשש. Mecharu beit din eino nimchar
ela l'shesh. המוכר עצמו אינו נרצע. Hamocher atzmo eino nirtza. Ah.
So let's continue the ברייתא, braita, sorry. So this is the same
ברייתא braita continuing, and the ברייתא braita continues. המוכר עצמו אינו נרצע,
Hamocher atzmo eino nirtza, if you sell yourself into slavery, your ear
will not be pierced, because you agreed to this arrangement. So then
the whole context of עבד נרצע eved nirtza doesn't even make sense
because you've agreed to enter into this contractual business deal, and then
you want to be able to get out of it, why would
you ever even want to do to become an עבד נרצע eved
nirtza at that point? עבד נרצע eved nirtza is about someone who
really was close to being enslaved to this family and so then
if he likes it, he'll be accepted. Tangential note, the last law
in Hammurabi's Code is what do you do if a slave runs
away, and the first law in פרשת משפטים Parshat Mishpatim is what
do you do when a slave says, "I want to stay enslaved."
So Rabbi Hertz in the Hertz חומש Chumash makes a point just
about the whole focal point of Judaism in rejection of the ancient
Near Eastern slave laws is to say the Jewish system is designed
in such a way that there is even a הוה אמינא hava
amina that a slave after six years will want to be a
slave because it's a good lifestyle and that's the kind of respect
and care that you should be treating workers and slaves with in
the תורה's Torah society. Okay. מכרוהו בית דין נרצע, Mecharu beit din
nirtza, but a מכרוהו בית דין mecharu beit din if he was
sold by בית דין beit din he could be have his ear
pierced. מוכר עצמו אין מעניקים לו Mocher atzmo ein ma'anikim lo and
מוכר עצמו mocher atzmo if you sold yourself into it, then when
you go free, there's no obligation to give you gifts of food
and supplies for your starting out in the severance pay kind of
thing. מכרוהו בית דין מעניקים לו Mecharu beit din ma'anikim lo and
that's one of the special מצוות mitzvot that the תורה Torah provides
for when the מכרוהו בית דין mecharu beit din goes free, the
master has to provide him with produce and food and money to
support himself. Now again, think about it. This is someone who was
incredibly poor such that he could not pay back what he stole.
So obviously if you're just going to send him back into the
world with nothing, that is, he paid off his debt and now
there's nothing left, zero, he's back in the black, but he's at
zero. He's going to go out into the world, what's his option
now? The only thing he can do basically, I mean he can
go and try to get a job somewhere, but he doesn't have
a place to live, he doesn't have any food, he doesn't have
any clothes, or he can go and steal again. So the תורה
Torah says הענק תעניק לו, ha'anek ta'anik lo, right? You have to
provide for him in order to give him that boost, that jump-start
to get back going. מוכר עצמו אין רבו מוסר לו שפחה כנענית
Mocher atzmo ein rabo moser lo shifcha knaanit and if you were
מוכר עצמו mocher atzmo if you sold yourself into the servitude then
the master cannot give you a שפחה כנענית shifcha knaanit to marry
and produce little baby עבדים avadim who are עבד כנעני, eved knaani,
but מכרוהו בית דין רבו מוסר לו שפחה כנענית. mecharu beit din
rabo moser lo shifcha knaanit. And if it was מכרוהו בית דין
mecharu beit din so this ברייתא, braita, this תנא tanna at least,
and this מחלוקת תנאים, machloket tanna'im, but this תנא tanna who quotes
in this ברייתא braita highlights many distinctions between מוכר עצמו mocher atzmo
and מכרוהו בית דין mecharu beit din which is pretty much based
on the פשט pshat in the פסוקים. psukim. That is other תנאים
tanna'im disagree and collapse the system. But this תנא tanna holds that
there are differences between מכרוהו בית דין mecharu beit din and מוכר
עצמו mocher atzmo based on the פשט pshat and actually highlights very
important difference that is מכרוהו בית דין mecharu beit din is much
closer to a real kind of slavery. That is this is in
a certain sense punishment and restitution and imprisonment for your crime, very
different than מוכר עצמו mocher atzmo which is basically a business deal
that someone who is down on their luck might make if they
needed to to make up some cash.
What's the status of the child of עבד
עברי eved ivri that מכרוהו בית דין? mecharu beit din? עבד עברי
eved ivri the child of the שפחה כנענית shifcha knaanit is an
עבד כנעני. eved knaani. Now we know שפחה כנענית shifcha knaanit is
as if partially Jewish, that is עבד עברי eved ivri and שפחה
כנענית shifcha knaanit are partially Jewish in that they have to keep
certain מצוות mitzvot but they are עבדים avadim it's a different status
and the children born to a שפחה כנענית shifcha knaanit are עבדים
avadim and therefore a good way for a slave owner to have
more slaves is יליד בית yelid bayit the תורה Torah talks about
slaves born. into your household, that is, if your slaves procreate, then
you own their offspring, and that's a way this way the תורה
Torah would provide an עבד עברי eved ivri even to be allowed
or forced even to procreate with שפחה כנענית shifcha canaanit in such
a way so as to produce more more slaves for the slave
master. Okay, רבי אלעזר אומר, Rabbi Elazar omer, זה וזה אינו נמכר
אלא לשש, zeh vezeh eino nimkar ela leshesh, זה וזה נרצע, zeh
vezeh nirtza, וזה וזה מעניקים לו, vezeh vezeh ma'anikim lo, וזה וזה
רבו מוסר לו שפחה כנענית. vezeh vezeh rabo moser lo shifcha canaanit.
So, this is a מחלוקת machloket between the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma
and רבי אלעזר. Rabbi Elazar. תנא קמא Tanna Kamma thinks there are
all these differences between מוכר עצמו mocher atzmo and מכרוהו בית דין,
mecharuhu beit din, and רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar thinks that they're basically
the same הלכה. halacha. That is, all of those distinctions are actually
collapsed. If we would take time to learn in the פסוקים, psukim,
you'll see the context makes it very clear that at the פשט
pshat level, all of those distinctions are in place. The תנא קמא
Tanna Kamma is very good at reading פשט, pshat, and רבי אלעזר
Rabbi Elazar says, whatever, the הלכה halacha system takes all the information
from the תורה Torah and condenses it into a single mechanism of
עבד עברי, eved ivri, not two parallel systems, one of מכרוהו בית
דין mecharuhu beit din and one of
מוכר עצמו. mocher atzmo. Okay, מאי לאו בהא קמיפלגי? mai lav be-ha
kamipalgi? So, what's the מחלוקת machloket about? דתנא קמא לא יליף שכיר
שכיר. de-Tanna Kamma lo yalif sachir sachir. It must be that the
תנא קמא Tanna Kamma does not learn the גזרה שוה gezera shava
from שכיר שכיר, sachir sachir, that is, the פסוקים psukim equating the
case of עבד עברי eved ivri in ויקרא Vayikra and in דברים,
Devarim, which were two different sources about עבד עברי. eved ivri. So,
the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma does not learn them, and therefore he
sees all these distinctions between those two different categories. So in ויקרא,
Vayikra, he sees it talking about מוכר עצמו; mocher atzmo; in דברים,
Devarim, he sees מכרוהו בית דין, mecharuhu beit din, and all of
the נפקא מינות nafka minot that came with that. ורבי אלעזר יליף
שכיר שכיר. ve-Rabbi Elazar yalif sachir sachir. רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar does
learn שכיר שכיר. sachir sachir. So now we know who holds what,
and we know both according to each of those שיטות, shitot, how
do we know that you could be an עבד עברי eved ivri
נקנה בכסף? nikneh be-chessef? אמר רב תביומי משמיה דאביי דכולי עלמא יליף
שכיר שכיר. Amar Rav Tavyumi mishmei de-Abaye dekulei alma yalif sachir sachir.
No, a different approach. The אמוראים Amoraim now say everyone agrees to
שכיר שכיר. sachir sachir. Everyone thinks that we can equate and draw
the parallels between the two different sources, make the גזרה שוה. gezera
shava. ובהאי קרא קמיפלגי. u-ve-hai kra kamipalgi. רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar and
the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma disagree about this פסוק. מאי טעמא דתנא
קמא? Mai ta’ama de-Tanna Kamma? אמר מוכר עצמו נמכר לשש ויתר על
לשש. Amar mocher atzmo nimkar leshesh ve-yeter al shesh. מיעט רחמנא גבי
מכרוהו בית דין ועבדך שש שנים. Mi'et rachmana gabei mecharuhu beit din
ve-avadcha shesh shanim. The תורה Torah made a special exclusion that מכרוהו
בית דין mecharuhu beit din could not work more than six years.
זה ולא מוכר עצמו. Zeh velo mocher atzmo. Only מכרוהו בית דין
mecharuhu beit din could work limited to six years, but מוכר עצמו
mocher atzmo could work for more. ואידך
ועבדך. ve-idach ve-avadcha. ועבדך לך ולא ליורש. ve-avadcha lecha velo le-yoresh. But
he, that is, the רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar, needs that פסוק, ועבדך.
ve-avadcha. He works for you, but if the אדון adon dies, then
he does not work for the יורש. yoresh. That is, עבד עברי
eved ivri is not inheritable property. He's not property. He's a Jewish
person; he's working for you. And if the person he made the
contract with dies, he doesn't transfer that contract to the יורש, yoresh,
he doesn't transfer it to the inheriting
son. ואידך ועבדך
אחרינא כתיב. ve-idach ve-avadcha achrina ketiv. And then the other opinion, that
is, תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma, ועבדך אחרינא כתיב, ve-avadcha achrina ketiv, afterwards.
ואידך ההוא להרצאת אדון הוא דאתא. ve-idach hahu lehartzat adon hu de-ata.
That comes to get the אדון, adon, that the אדון adon agreed
to it. מאי טעמא דתנא קמא דאמר מוכר עצמו אינו נרצע? Mai
ta’ama de-Tanna Kamma de-amar mocher atzmo eino nirtza? So how then—so let's
pause here because it's going to come up tomorrow—but just going through
each of these distinctions now and saying, even if both תנא קמא
Tanna Kamma and רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar agree that we do learn
the דרשה שכיר שכיר, sachir sachir, nonetheless, how do they get all
of their distinctions?